Using the Ripple for introduction to Python, we worked exclusively in the Ripple for intermediate Python we're going to be working in both the Ripple and in Python files.
Ripple stands for Read Evaluate Print Loop. It's the interactive Python interpreter that lets us type commands in and quickly see the output.
Unlike running your Python code in a file, you also don't necessarily need to display any output in a print statement.
You can just type in the name of a variable and the Ripple will show you its value.
This is really quick for great for quick prototyping debugging as a Python developer.
I've worked in Python for six years. I still have a Ripple open daily so that I can experiment with my code, look at documentation.
Very quickly, et cetera. So in VS code to open the Ripple, we're going to go to VS code, use the keyboard shortcut for our command palette for Mac that's command shift P and we're going to select Start Ripple.
And that should open a Ripple here at the bottom.
Now, I think that the best way to learn a language, the best way to learn anything is just typing along muscle memory.
So I recommend that as I'm coding and as I'm showing concepts and as I'm experimenting that all of the students follow along in the Ripple live.
That's how you'll get the most value out of this class. Just a quick tour of the Ripple.
These three arrows here means it's a prompt. It's ready for input. So I can type stuff in here. If I just type the name of a variable, I'll see that output.
If I start an if statement for example, I'll see these three dots here and that means that the Ripple is awaiting more input.
So here I would have to provide a level of indentation and say, you know, the rest of my statements.
As you notice in an if statement, the first time I press enter when I'm done with my code block.
I still see these three dots still waiting for input. So in the Ripple, we'll have to press enter just one more time to make sure that this command is executed successfully.
Throughout the course, you will see code that looks like this. If you see these right arrows here and this label that says Python Ripple, that means that the file is running the Ripple.
Otherwise, you'll see Python file and that means run this code from a Python file.
You can copy and paste my Python Ripple code. Maybe occasionally you'll see a little bit of a blip.
And then you can paste it right into your Ripple. You'll just have to hit enter to run the last command. That's how I make sure that you're awake.
Okay.
This three most important commands for the Ripple are type, der and help.
So if I'm not sure about the type of something, I can call the built in type class and pass in my variable.
Let me know that A was of class int.
Let's say I have a string here.
If I want to know all of the method available on string because, you know, we're not Google as programmers. We don't have to memorize these things.
I can type, I can use the built in der function here and pass in a class.
So very quickly, if I look for the type of name, type of name.
Oops, I'm so sorry, cannot type this morning.
So I'm pressing Ctrl C to kind of exit the statement as I, if I make a mistake.
So type of name is stir. I can do der on on stir. That's the class right here.
And that will show me all of the methods available on the string class.
The ones that we care about are the ones that don't start with the underscores or double underscores. You can kind of consider those to be private methods.
And let's say I don't remember what upper does.
This is where help comes in. So I can pass in either a whole type to help.
And I don't show me all of the help for all of the methods.
Or if I just want to zoom in on a particular function here, I could do stir.
And then I would just type the name of the method that I'm interested in.
No additional parentheses here or anything.
And this will bring up help a little bit of documentation. It'll show me what arguments are required if any.
And usually a helpful message. Sometimes not so much to exit out of the screen. Just hit Q.
Okay. So that's the tour of the Ripple. I recommend everybody has one open.
So running code will be working with the mix of the Ripple and Python files in day two.
New Python files have a .py extension. To create them, just hit command n or control n, depending on your operating system.
And then you'll have to save that file as a .py file in order for VS code to recognize that it's working with Python.
Once you do that, you should see syntax highlighting. You should see linting if you installed your linter. You'll have auto complete.
A lot of kind of really nice helpful things there.
So you don't have to follow along here, but if I make a new file.
And I print out, you know, paste in this from the class website.
So it's all white, right? I'm not seeing any syntax highlighting. So what I have to do is save that file as hello.py. I see all my syntax highlighting.
To run this file, very quickly and easily in using the correct interpreter.
You would have to open your command palette, command shift P, Python run Python file in terminal.
Easy peasy.
Lastly, the VS code terminal window. It'll automatically pop up if you start the Ripple, run the Python file from the command palette.
To quickly open and close the Ripple on Mac, it's control and backtick.
As we see here on Windows, I believe it's control and single quote that will open and close the Ripple for you.
An important thing to know about the Ripple. If you click here in this dropdown box, these are all your different, I'm sorry, if an important thing about the terminal.
If you click here in this dropdown box, you'll see tabs for all your different terminals. You'll have your Ripple here, your Python. Maybe a shell. This is how you can switch between them.
Okay, that's the whirlwind tour of VS code.